Finding Aid for Michigan Archaeological Society records, 1924-2015
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Archaeological Society records 1924-2015 1956-2010
Michigan Archaeological Society.
851849 Bp 2
Organization concerned with the exploration of the cultures, artifacts, and peoples of early Michigan; records include background information, administrative files, local chapter materials, and topical files.
5.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were obtained in several accessions: through Ira Butterfield (donor no. 5169 ) in 1971 and 1992, and from the Michigan Archaeological Society (donor nos. 5063 and 6949 ) in 2008, 2013, and 2014.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Archaeological Society (MAS) is an amateur association concerned with the cultures, artifacts, and peoples of early Michigan. It was officially incorporated as a non-profit organization in 1954. The origins of the MAS, however, go back to 1924, when a group of professional and amateur archaeologists decided that "a united effort was necessary to assemble the data at hand and further search for additional evidence of man's early occupancy in Michigan" (Box 1, Background folder). Unfortunately, the beginning of the Depression meant the end of the fledgling MAS at the time.
Although many MAS members continued their interest in, and commitment to, archaeology, working in small, informal groups, the MAS was not rejuvenated until 1950. It was Emerson F. Greenman, of the University of Michigan's Museum of Anthropology, who reorganized the Society, following the tradition of close ties between professionals and amateurs. Within the MAS, both professionals and amateurs pursued the same goals: "to investigate, research, record, and conserve archaeological sites and artifacts; to cooperate with universities, colleges, and museums with similar interests; and to exchange and disseminate information on such subjects" (Box 1, Background folder).
Over the years, the MAS has been involved in several projects ranging from highway salvage to site surveys to the preservation of petroglyphs. In the process, they have dealt and cooperated with numerous state agencies, museums, colleges, as well as peer archaeological groups in Michigan and in other states.
The MAS operates as a statewide "umbrella" organization made up of local chapters in various Michigan cities. Chapters currently, or at one time, associated with the Michigan Archaeological Society include Blue Ridge Chapter, Central Michigan Chapter, Clinton Valley Chapter, Genesee Chapter, Kalamazoo Chapter, Little Forks Chapter, Newaygo Chapter, River Raisin Chapter (Monroe), Saginaw Chapter, South Central Chapter, Southeastern Chapter, Southwest Chapter, Upper Grand Valley Chapter, Upper Peninsula Chapter, and Wright L. Coffinberry Chapter (Grand Rapids).
The records of the Michigan Archaeological Society records cover the period since 1924. The record group consists primarily of reports, meeting agenda and minutes, correspondence, newsletters and clippings. The series in the record group are: Background, Administrative, Activities, Local Chapters, and Topical.
Subjects:
Archaeology.; Eastern States Archeological Federation (U.S.); Indians of North America--Michigan.; Michigan Archaeological Society.; Sanilac County (Mich.); Michigan--Antiquities.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Archaeology.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Mecosta County (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Background
  The Background series includes bylaws, operating structure, and constitutions from several different years (to show the changes from one period to the next).
  - Bylaws, operating structure, and constitution 1955-1982, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series is comprised of the usual organizational materials--agendas and minutes, newsletters, correspondence, and reports. However, a substantive part of this series is the long run of annual meeting materials from 1956 to 2014. Arranged by year, these records summarize the activities and concerns of the MAS. These records also show the hierarchy of the organization in any given year. At each meeting, annual reports were given by the president, the treasurer, and the presidents of local chapters. The Society's annual reports to the Eastern States Archaeological Federation (ESAF), of which it is a member, are included in this series because this is when the reports are presented to MAS members. Although not every year is consistently documented with the same amount or the same kinds of reports, taken as an aggregate, the annual meeting records are an invaluable retrospective source showing how the MAS changed and grew over an extended period of time.
  Also illuminating within the Administrative series, despite the obvious chronological gaps, are the general and president's correspondence, as well as both the state and executive boards' agendas and minutes. All of these records are arranged by year in ascending order, although only the agendas and minutes are arranged chronologically therein. Given that these records span from the earliest years of the Society's incorporation in the 1950s, up to the 2000s, they complement the set of annual meeting reports and fill in the details that annual reports can only summarize. The correspondence mainly documents three things: 1) archaeological work done by MAS members, 2) organizational structure, or 3) the MAS' relationship with other associations, agencies, or institutions. The president's correspondence especially shows how each president shaped the objectives and activities of the MAS during his one-year term.
  - Accounting Ledger 1973-1979 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Bulletins 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting
    - 1952 (Box 1)
      (Paper given at meeting, "Ancient Mounds Near Grand Rapids")
    - 1956-2007 2013-2014 (Box 1)
  - Auditor's Reports 1956, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - General (lists of committees) 1962-1964, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Archives Committee 1956 (Box 1)
    - Filmstrip Committee 1956-1958, undated (Box 1)
    - Membership Committee 1956-1978 (Box 1)
    - Nominating Committee 1956 (Box 1)
    - Publications Committee 1956, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Executive Board
    - Agendas and Minutes
      (including some treasurer's reports)
      - 1956-1965 (Box 2)
      - 1966-1977, 1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1985 (Box 2)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
      - 1991 (Box 2)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 2)
      - 1994 (Box 2)
      - 1995 (Box 2)
      - 1996 (Box 2)
      - 1997 (Box 2)
      - 1998 (Box 2)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 2)
      - 2001-2002 (Box 2)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 2)
      - 2005 (Box 2)
      - 2006 (Box 2)
      - 2007-2008 (Box 2)
      - 2009 (Box 2)
      - 2010-2011 (Box 2)
      - 2012 (Box 2)
      - 2013 (Box 2)
      - 2015 (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1953-1956 (Box 6)
    - 1957-1961 (Box 6)
    - 1962-1964, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
    - 1969, 1971-1974 (Box 6)
    - 1976-1983 (Box 6)
    - Undated (Box 6)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 6)
      (James Ebert)
  - Newsletters 1954-1956, 1965-1970, 1972-1973, 1984-1986 (Box 6)
  - Non-Profit Organization Reports (including licenses to solicit donations) 1965-1966, 1969-1973 (Box 6)
  - President's Files (primarily consists of correspondence before 1976)
    - 1956 (Box 6)
      (Ira Butterfield)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 6)
      (Harold Moll)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 6)
      (Leonard Griffin)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 6)
      (William Beverly)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 6)
      (Don Hagge)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 6)
      (W. D. Frankforter)
    - 1972-1984, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 6)
      (Barbara Young)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 3)
      (Robert Woodhams)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 3)
      (Lawrence G. Dorothy)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 3)
      (Donna Sanford)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 3)
      (Lorena Martin)
  - Publicity
    - Clippings (Box 3)
    - News Releases and Miscellaneous 1968, 1969, undated (Box 3)
  - Report of Conference with Michigan Department of Natural Resources 1969 (Box 3)
  - State Board
    - Agendas and Minutes
      - 1956-1971 (Box 3)
      - 1976-1981 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer's Reports 1955-1969, 2014 (Box 3)
- Activities
  In the Activities series documents the annual workshop conferences material and other MAS events and projects. The series is comprised of fliers and printed programs, and project correspondence and documents.
  - Annual Workshop Conferences 1956-1990, 2014 (Box 3)
    (including photographs for the 11-4-62 conference and four Edison Voicewriter Discs)
  - Educational Programs 1967, 1971, 1979, undated (Box 3)
  - Essay Award 1987 (Box 3)
  - Fall Workshop 1994-2007 (Box 3)
  - Highway Archaeological Salvage Program 1957-1959, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Library Project (publications drive) 1958 (Box 3)
  - Sanilac Petroglyphs Project
    - Agendas and Minutes 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - 1956-1958 (Box 3)
      - 1965-1967 (Box 3)
      - 1968 (Box 3)
      - 1969 (Box 3)
      - 1974 (Box 3)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Legal Documents (including trust agreement and affidavit) 1965, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Proposal to Mott Foundation 1968 (Box 3)
    - Relm Foundation Grant 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - State Survey Project 1985 (Box 3)
- Local Chapters
  Local Chapters series contains the records of the MAS's multiple current and past local chapters. The series includes the local chapter's constitutions, meeting minutes and notices, newsletters, and clippings.
  - General Chapter Records 1966-1968 (Box 3)
  - Blue Ridge Chapter
    - Constitution undated (Box 3)
  - Central Michigan Chapter
    - Correspondence 1965, undated (Box 3)
    - Newsletter 1957 (Box 3)
  - Clinton Valley Chapter
    - Annual Report 2014 (Box 3)
    - Background (including constitution) undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1967-1968, 1971, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Membership Interest Survey 1975 (Box 3)
    - Minutes (1962-1965) and Accounts (1965-1967) (Box 3)
      (in one booklet)
    - Minutes and Notices of Meetings
      (agendas)
      - 1965-1968 (Box 3)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 3)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 3)
      - 1975 (Box 3)
      - 1976 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (archaeological handouts) undated (Box 3)
    - Newsletters 1962, 1965, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Publicity (news releases and clippings) 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Genesee Chapter
    - Constitution and bylaws 1966, undated (Box 3)
    - Minutes and Notices of Meetings 1956-1974, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - President's Book 1966-1976 (Box 3)
    - Proposed Code of Ethics 1956 (Box 4)
  - Huron Valley Chapter
    - Annual Report 2014 (Box 4)
  - Kalamazoo Chapter
    - Constitution undated (Box 4)
    - Minutes and Notices of Meetings (agendas) 1966-1973 (Box 4)
  - Little Forks Chapter
    - Constitution 1980 (Box 4)
  - Newaygo Chapter
    - Background (including constitution) 1966, undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1965 (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1965 (Box 4)
    - Newsletters 1965-1968 (Box 4)
  - Northwest Chapter
    - Constitution undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1980 (Box 4)
  - River Raisin Chapter (Monroe)
    - Background (including constitution) 1981, undated (Box 4)
    - Annual Fall Workshop ("In Pursuit of the Paleo Hunter, Part II") 1981 (Box 4)
    - Annual Report 2014 (Box 4)
    - Calendar of Programs and Events 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - Highway Archaeological Survey 1972 (Box 4)
    - Minutes and Notices of Meetings (agendas) 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Report to Michigan Council for the Arts ("In Pursuit of the Paleo Hunter") 1973 (Box 4)
  - Saginaw Valley Chapter
    - Announcements of Activities 1961, 1964, 1975, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports 1953, 2014 (Box 4)
    - Annual Treasurer's Reports 1965-1970, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Constitution and Bylaws 1955, 1965, 1983 and proposed changes, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1956-1965, 1983-1986, undated (Box 4)
    - Executive Board Minutes
      - 1965-1968 (Box 4)
      - 1983-1987 (Box 4)
    - Minutes and Notices of Meetings
      - 1956-1961 undated (Box 4)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 4)
      - 1966-1969 (Box 4)
      - 1975-1979 (Box 4)
      - 1981-1984 (Box 4)
      - 1985-1991 (Box 4)
    - Newsletters 1976-1977, undated (Box 4)
    - Proposed Resolution (site number regulations) 1963 (Box 4)
    - Saginaw Valley Archaeologist, sales and inventory 1984 (Box 4)
  - South Central Chapter
    - Constitution undated (Box 4)
  - Southeast Chapter (Box 4)
  - Southeastern Chapter
    - Newsletters 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - Southwest Chapter
    - Announcements of Meetings and Events 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - Newsletters
      - 1953-1958 (Box 4)
      - 1959-1963 (Box 4)
      - 1964-1968 (Box 4)
      - 1969-1974 undated (Box 4)
  - Thunder Bay Chapter
    - Annual Report 2014 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified Chapter
    - Minutes 1968 (Box 4)
  - Upper Grand Valley Chapter
    - Annual Report 2014 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1974, undated (Box 4)
    - Newsletters 1966, 1972-1979 (Box 4)
  - Upper Peninsula Chapter
    - Constitution undated (Box 4)
  - Wright L. Cofffinberry Chapter (Grand Rapids)
    - Background (including constitutions) 1951, 1958, 1964, undated (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports 1960, 1966, 2014 (Box 4)
    - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1970 (Box 4)
    - Executive Board Minutes
      - 1952-1963 (Box 4)
      - 1965-1968 (Box 4)
      - 1969-1971 (Box 4)
      - 1972-1975 (Box 4)
    - Memoranda 1951-1952, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Minutes
      - 1951-1963 (Box 4)
      - 1959, 1965-1967 (Box 4)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 4)
      - 1971-1975 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (including essays on archaeological topics) undated (Box 5)
    - Newell E. Collins Correspondence (incoming) 1940-1956 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters
      - 1962-1968 (Box 5)
      - 1969-1975 (Box 5)
      - 1976-1983 (Box 5)
    - Photographs (Box 5)
      (Native American chief in ceremonial dress, miscellaneous artifacts, and an archaeological site)
    - Programs 1955-1956, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Secretary's Corner
      - 1959-1961 (Box 5)
      - 1965-1969 (Box 5)
      - 1970-1971, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Secretary's Page 1973-1975 (Box 5)
    - Treasurer's Reports 1957-1958 (Box 5)
- Topical
  In the Topical series (0.25 linear feet), most of the headings, arranged alphabetically, are self-explanatory, except for "George R. Fox." Like that of "Newell E. Collins" in the Saginaw Valley Chapter records, Fox's correspondence represents the only way to access the earlier history of the Michigan Archaeological Society (the first one) and the beginnings of archaeology in Michigan.
  - Archaeological Act 1972-1973 (Box 5)
  - Archaeological Survey of the Muskegon Pipeline 1957 (Box 5)
  - Archives Correspondence 1991-2008 (Box 5)
  - Biographies (various members) 1962, 1963, 2000s, undated (Box 5)
  - Captain Lawrence (shipwreck Litigation) 1995 (Box 5)
  - Certification 1973-1974, undated (Box 5)
  - Descriptions of Archaeological Sites 1965, undated (Box 5)
  - Eastern States Archaeological Federation (EASF, correspondence and miscellaneous) 1956-1968 (Box 5)
  - George R. Fox Papers
    - Correspondence 1924, 1927, 1929, undated (Box 5)
    - Microfilm Negative (Indian arrowheads from different townships, archaeological atlas, and Fox Indians) 1958 (Box 5)
  - Grant Proposal to Michigan Council for the Humanities undated (Box 5)
  - Inventory of Talents and Interests 1956 (Box 5)
  - Legislation 1971-1973 (Box 5)
  - Photographs 1924-1981, undated (Box 5)
  - MAS Seal 1957, undated (Box 5)
  - Proposal for Bicentennial Archaeology Publication Program 1975 (Box 5)
  - Proposal for a Michigan archaeological survey undated (ca. 1970) and responses, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
  - Society for American Archaeology (correspondence) 1957 (Box 5)